<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An homily upon these words of Saint Matthew, chap. 16.v.18 Tu es Petrus. Written first in French by that honorable and learned personage, Monsieur Du Plessis Mornay. And translated into English by I.V.</title>
            <title>Homélie sur ces mots de sainct Matthieu. English.</title>
            <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100069</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835921</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07764)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1281:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An homily upon these words of Saint Matthew, chap. 16.v.18 Tu es Petrus. Written first in French by that honorable and learned personage, Monsieur Du Plessis Mornay. And translated into English by I.V.</title>
                  <title>Homélie sur ces mots de sainct Matthieu. English.</title>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
                  <author>Verneuil, John, 1582 or 3-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, Printer to the Universitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A12 B6 (A1 possibly blank, lacking).</note>
                  <note>I.V. = John Verneuil?--STC.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Mornay, Phillippe de.  Homélie sur ces mots de Sainct Matthieu, chap.16, vers.18: Tu es Petrus.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained or torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN HOMILY VPON THESE WORDS of Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> Chap. 16. v. 18.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Tu es Petrus.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>WRITTEN FIRST in French by that <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and learned perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage,</hi> Monſieur Du PLES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIS MORNAY. AND TRANSLATED into Engliſh by I. V.</p>
            <p>AT OXFORD. Printed by <hi>Ioſeph Barnes,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>to the Vniverſitie.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:154:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull and Reverend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> DOCTOR PRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEAVX Rector of Exceter Colledge, my moſt Reſpected <hi>good Maſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; Reverend Sir, I am bolde to preſent vnto your Worſh: my moſt endebted ſervice, vnder the vaile of this little booke. It is the pen, and word muſt ſerue you, not the ſword: what though my quil be dull, and the glorious light of the originall of this worke bee clowded and obſcured by mine
<pb facs="tcp:154:3"/>vnskilfull tranſlation: yet aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don you it not vtterly, but loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on the luſtre of the ſetting ſunne, that Aged Head, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got this, thinke that the obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity here cannot be ſo Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-like, but that ſome rayes may nevertheleſſe haue power to ſhine? The Author is a true Champion of the Militant-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed-French Church, long trained vp vnder her ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derd. For having already valiantly fought both with pen &amp; ſword, he is yet ambitious in her ſervice: either viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to chaſe the old Gooſe out of the Capitoll: or to<note n="*" place="margin">Miſt. Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit in epiſt. ad Regem Mag. Brita.</note> finde a glorious tombe in the ſnow of the Alpes. Let him bee an Apologie for my boldnes, and a perſwaſion to humbly entreat your Worſhip to accept this ſmall duty of mine; which if you ſhall be pleaſed ſo kindly to doe, as I with all humility doe offer it: you will ſo encourage
<pb facs="tcp:154:3"/>me, that if higher meanes bee wanting I ſhall further ſtriue in this kinde hereafter to ſhew my ſelfe in all manner of ſervice.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips moſt humble and faithfull ſervant, <hi>I. V.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:154:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN HOMILY VPON theſe words of S. Mathew chapt. 16. verſ. 18. <hi>Tu es Petrus, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Lord Ieſus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, <hi>whom do men ſay that J the ſonne of man am?</hi> The man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſe.</hi> 13.</note> in whom for outwarde apparancy, they ſaw nothing but man: and they anſwered him, <hi>Some ſay that thou art John Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſe.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Some Elias, and others Jeremias, or one of the Prophets,</hi> for without doubt through that humanity, and that infirmity they ſaw ſome vertues, and puiſſance ſhine in him aboue the perfections of man. <hi>But whom ſay ye</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that Jam?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſe.</hi> 15.</note> To which <hi>Simm Peter</hi> ſomewhat forwarder then the reſt, (were it in regard of his zeale, or in reſpect of his knowledge) frames this reply. <hi>Thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</hi> Not one of the Prophets;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſe.</hi> 16.</note> they were his Heraulds; but the end of all the Prophets: not <hi>John Baptiſt;</hi> hee was his forerunner: but that eternall word, of which he was but the voice which cryed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154:5"/>in the wildernes, the ſonne of the living God, begotten from all eternity, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the beginning of time, exhibited in the fulnes of times, for the ranſome, the life, and the everlaſting ſalvation of the world, even of thoſe whom it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to redeeme from the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and perdition of the world; And to that, what ſaith our Saviour? What ſaith that ſonne of the living God, whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine word in ſo high a ſubiect, promiſeth nothing humane, nothing terreſtriall, nothing which tends not to everlaſting ſalvation, and the kingdome of heaven? <hi>Bleſſed art thou Simon Bar-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ona, ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fleſh and bloud hath not revealed it vnto thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſe.</hi> 17.</note> hence therefore all carnall, all temporall ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, <hi>But my father which is in heaven,</hi> my father which by me in this revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and this faith diſpenſeth his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graces, <hi>But J ſay alſo vnto thee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that thou art Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſe.</hi> 18.</note> ſuch a one would I haue thee to be called, and ſuch a one would I haue thee to be indeede; the names which I impoſe are vocations, with the names I can change the nature and quality of things, <hi>Vpon this rocke J will build my church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it.</hi> Theſe laſt words are thoſe which wee are to expound, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154:5"/>admit divers interpretations, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will ſearch out that which ſhall bee moſt agreeable to our purpoſe in hand, and ſhall holde beſt analogy, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and correſpondencie with this holy catechiſme.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Thou art Peter</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>and vpon this rocke I will build my Church</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Here a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on offereth it ſelfe to be decided, to wit, whether our Saviour in theſe words, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to build his Church vpon <hi>Simon,</hi> by him ſurnamed <hi>Peter,</hi> or vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Chriſt the Sonne of the living God, acknowledged and confeſſed by <hi>Peter.</hi> Concerning which wee muſt obſerue that our Saviour then when he changed his name, ſaid vnto him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.42.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Cephas which is by interpretation a ſtone,</hi> and that in the Syriaque tongue, which our Saviour vſed, ſome ambiguity may bee found, in as much as that the word <hi>Cephas</hi> without any alteration of the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſignifieth both <hi>Peter</hi> the ſurname of <hi>Simon,</hi> and likewiſe a ſtone. But our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt, or (to ſay rather) the ſpirit of God which both ſpake &amp; wrote in him, being willing to eaſe vs ſomewhat in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the difficulty, vvould giue vs no cauſe to miſtake one <hi>Cephas</hi> for an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, either to ſtumble at this <hi>Peter</hi> or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154:6"/>that ſtone, but tels vs in the authentique Greeke, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vvhich in our vulgar tranſlation canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by the councell of Trent is, <hi>Tu es Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus &amp; ſuper hanc petram,</hi> not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>ſuprate Petrum,</hi> vpon this ſtone, &amp; not vpon this <hi>Peter:</hi> otherwiſe vvhat had it beene to him if he had ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and how many difficulties, what tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults alſo and bloudy diſcords hath hee prevented by it? And if the maine ſcope of theſe wordes (as ſome would haue them) were meerely to giue authoritie vnto <hi>S. Peter,</hi> vvherefore did our Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt here leaue vs to our ſelues &amp; raiſe a ſcruple in this changing of <hi>Peter,</hi> and in the difference which he puts between the one, and the other to ſtirre vs vp to a contention, but that it was to reſolue vs abſolutely of this, that ſeeing this changing proceeding from the ſpirit of God was not in vaine, Chriſt by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence did build his Church vpon himſelfe the ſonne of the eternall God, vvhich was the living rocke, and not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a man ſubiect to paſſion and morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, hovv excellent ſo ever he were, and therefore not vpon <hi>Peter.</hi> And indeed he which ſhall looke narrowly into it, vvill finde that according to the faſhion of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154:6"/>the Hebrewes this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in theſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is rather a particle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſatiue then comunctiue, as if our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſhould haue ſaid vnto him; Behold <hi>Simon</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Jona,</hi> thou that of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> vvhich thou wert, I haue made <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas;</hi> of duſt, aſhes, and ſlime which thou wert naturally vnprofitable for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding which I prepared, through a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar grace I haue made <hi>Peter,</hi> a living ſtone, a ſtone which hereafter may haue a place, and that a notable one in the building. But ſee likewiſe an other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; it is vpon thy confeſſion that Chriſt is the ſonne of God, which thou haſt confeſſed, vpon that ſtone vvhich thou ſeeſt, vpon that which I ſhevv thee, will I build my Church. In the ſame ſenſe that he ſaid <hi>deſtroy this temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19.</note> ſpeaking of his body, and ſhewed it vnto the Iewes, he ſaid likewiſe <hi>vpon this rocke,</hi> vpon mee the eternal rocke wil I build my church, and ſhewed himſelfe both to <hi>Peter</hi> and his other diſciples.</p>
            <p n="3">3 But againſt ſo many preiudicated contrarieties, thou wouldeſt not haue mee for an interpreter, whome then wouldeſt thou vvillingly accept? our Lord Chriſt, ſhall hee bee authentique vvith thee vvhich heere ſpeaketh, or els
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154:7"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi> to vvhom hee ſpeaketh? Heare therefore Chriſt ſpeaking to the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal ſacrificers and ancients of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Did yee neuer reade in the Scriptures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.42.</note> 
               <hi>That ſtone which the builders refuſed, the ſame is become the head of the corner.</hi> In conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſpeakes he this of <hi>Peter,</hi> or of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? Hath he not a reference vnto that place of the Prophet <hi>Eſay, Thus ſaith the Lord God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 28.16.</note> 
               <hi>behold I lay in Sion for a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a ſtone, a tried ſtone, a precious corner ſtone, a ſare foundation, he that beleeueth ſhall not make haſt,</hi> that is, hee ſhall not ſtumble like thoſe that fall.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>Iudgement alſo will I lay to the line, and righteouſneſſe to the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> &amp;c. Was there euer any ancient or moderne Greeke or Latine vvhich vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it othervviſe then of Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, his Meſſias? Harken moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnto <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe, becauſe ſome vvould intereſt <hi>Peter</hi> againſt vs in this paſſage,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Approch you neere vnto Chriſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which is a luung ſtone diſallowed indeed of men, but choſen of God, and precious,</hi> this is that ſtone which vve ſeeke, but vvould you ſee vvhat ranke <hi>Peter</hi> holdeth? <hi>yee as liuely ſtones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 5.</note> liuely indeed through that quickning ſtone, that ſtone lifted vp on high, <hi>are built vp a ſpirituall houſe, an holy Preieſthood to offer vp ſpirituall ſacrifice, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154:7"/>to God by Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> In conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence againe in the language of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtle thinkeſt thou that he preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be the foundation of this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall edifice? eſteemed he not himſelfe to be honored and graced ſufficiently in that hee vvas ſet vpon that ſtone, nay would he not haue took it as a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered him, if any ſhould haue alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vnto him in preiudice of that which was ſpoken of Chriſt alone, theſe words <hi>Tu es Petrus, Thou art Peter?</hi> And indeed Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in one word tells vs this, <hi>That other foundation can no man lay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>then that is laid, which is Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Chriſt then is the foundation, the liuing rock vvhich vvee ſeeke, and not <hi>Peter;</hi> but vpon this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, the maſter builders do lay there fundamentall ſtones, vvhereof S. <hi>Paul,</hi> vvhich vvas one of them, in the ſame place ſpeaketh in theſe vvords,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the grace of God which is giuen vnto me, as a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe maſter builder I haue laid the foundation, and another buildeth thereon;</hi> a foundation then vvas laid, and a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation vpon vvhich others lay on: the one, is Chriſt the liuing and quickening ſtone: the other, all faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, liuing ſtones by him quickned; amongſt which both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> may
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154:8"/>by good right hold place both of liuing ſtones, as being faithfull, and as being Miniſters of the holy Goſpell, and of shilfull builders, according to that which he ſaith in another place, that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. <hi>we built vpon the foundation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20.21.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe being the chiefe corner ſtone, In whom</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>all the building fitly framed together, groweth vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> holy Temple in the Lord:</hi> if vpon Chriſt the chiefe corner ſtone, then not vpon <hi>Peter;</hi> if vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, yet againe vpon Chriſt, if you vnderſtand it of that ſtone vpon vvhich they did lye, and if of thoſe ſtones, which in the nature of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter builders vvere laid thereupon, yet truely no more vpon <hi>Peter,</hi> then vpon any other of the Apoſtles. And to ſay the truth, all the Fathers, both Greeke, and Latine, haue found no other ſenſe, vvho very often doe tell vs, <hi>vpon this rock</hi> (that is to ſay) <hi>vpon the confeſſion of</hi> Peter, <hi>vpon Chriſt confeſſed by</hi> Peter, Peter <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being founded vpon Chriſt, Peter</hi> (ſay they) vvas no more authorized in this paſſage then the other Apoſtles, for vvhom he ſpake, and vvho had the ſame beleefe; and if any of them in any place chanced to ſay vpon <hi>Peter,</hi> he interprets
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154:8"/>and tempers himſelfe elſevvhere, euen Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> retracted and corrected himſelfe, for hauing vnderſtood <hi>Petras</hi> for <hi>petra, Peter</hi> for the <hi>ſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The nature of this building vvhich is novv in controuerſie, vvill cleare the truth of this interpretation, for this Church, the Church ſo properly called, the myſticall body of Chriſt, compoſed of all the elect, vvhich ſhall be vnto the end of the world (for of that only it may be ſaid, <hi>that the gates of hell,</hi> that all the aſſaults and ſtratagems of Satan cannot preuaile againſt it) vpon vvhat, hovv, and by whom is it builtiſurely vpon the confeſſion of <hi>Peter,</hi> vpon Chriſt confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be the Sonne of God by <hi>Peter,</hi> by the Apoſtles, and by all the faithfull; for without Chriſt, the eternall Sonne of God, there is no Church, there is no place vvhere to fixe the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone of the Church, according to that boaſting of Saint <hi>Paul, God forbid that I ſhould glory ſaue in the croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world is crucified vnto me &amp; I vnto the world:</hi> for in the death and ſufferings of Chriſt conſiſts the being and the well being, the life and the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of the Church, and how was it built? Certainly this maner of ſpeech,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154:9"/>like as are many others in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, is taken out of the Old; vnder the law is mentioned the building of the temple, &amp; vnder the Goſpell this tearm yet doth continue to build the Church. And as that was built of dead ſtones, ſo this of living ſtones, living Cephas's which are gathered together, ioyned &amp; inſerted into the worke, outwardly by the preaching of the Apoſtles, &amp; other ſervants of God, every one of them in their time, inwardly by the efficacie which the holy Ghoſt gaue to that word and through the bleſſing which God diſplaied by his graces vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which he imployed in his worke, opening both the eare and the heart of thoſe to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was preached, that they might heare it with reverence and receaue it with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. And therefore it is ſaid in the Acts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.31.</note> 
               <hi>that the Churches throughout Iudea, Galilee, and Samaria were edified,</hi> to wit, by the preaching of the word, that was the outward meanes, <hi>and in the comfort of the holy Ghoſt were multiplied,</hi> there was the inward. Now as for the inward, what man is he, be he never ſo arrogant, that daies boaſt of it, and as concerning the outward, what ſhall he bee, bee it what meaſure of grace it will that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154:9"/>of God, that it can ſuffice him, not only for the whole world, but even for the ſmalleſt province; Adde that the Church being perpetuall, and Peter mortall, there can be no proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the labour of Peter which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth with his life, and the building of the Church which is perpetuated through all ages, otherwiſe it ſhould haue fallen to ruine and tumbled down in the perſon of Peter; But thou wilt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect what order or what meanes hath Chriſt left vs for his outward miniſtery? heare the Apoſtle, <hi>when be aſcended vp on high, he led captivitie captiue, and gaue gifts vnto men,</hi> what gifts?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>he gaue ſome to bee A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, &amp; ſome Paſtors and teachers,</hi> why? <hi>for the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the Saints, for the worke of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till we all come in the vnitie of the faith, &amp; of the knowledge of the ſonne of God vnto a perfect man, vnto the meaſure of the ſtature of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt.</hi> Doſt thou not ſee how hee hath provided to bring his work even to its perfection? and that without mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at all either of Peter for his prince<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Apoſtle, or any other miniſteriall head of the Church? and where S. Paule ſpeakes ſo expreſly and ſo punctually
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154:10"/>in handling this matter, ought wee to ſupply his ſenſe, nay rather are wee not bound to hold our peace? committing that which remaines to the managing of our Lord the maſter of the houſe, who alwaies in the palme of his hand doth beare its portraiture, and conducts it with his ſpirit, and having ſaid to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles parting from beneath, <hi>Preach you to all nations, baptize you &amp;c.</hi> that is to ſay, performe your dutie every one of you in his place,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</note> every one in your vocation; and this holy miniſtery, hee added for their inward meanes, <hi>And loe I am with you alway even vnto the end of the world:</hi> Chriſt you ſee the ſonne of God of the ſame eſſence with his father nor leſſe je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his glory, and therefore, giue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not to another, or to any creature, which he ſhould haue done, if on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould haue cauſed, or ſuffered to depend the ſalvation of his Church.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Let vs ſay moreover, that al Scripture (as the Apoſtle teacheth vs) is giuen vs ☞ for the conſolation of the faithfull,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim</hi> 3.16.</note> &amp; we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not deny that the ſcope of theſe words of Chriſt is to fortifie his Diſciples a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the temptations and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which they were to expect by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the infallible continuance of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154:10"/>Church. Tell me therefore thou Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt, where ſindeſt thou moſt comfort in thy perplexities, where moſt refreſhings in thy ſoule, when one tels thee that the Church of Chriſt is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the faith of Peter, or vpon the true rocke which hee did here confeſſe, vpon Cephas a mortall man, yet a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſubiect to the like infirmities that wee are, the congealed rocke which the wether conſumes, or vpon the ſonne of God that eternal rock, that rocke which notwithſtanding its firmneſſe, diſſolved into the waters of comfort to quench thy thirſt, and diſtilled in hony to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thee in a deſart &amp; barren countrey? Verily if thou ſtandeſt yet vnreſolved in thy choyce, harken vnto Chriſt &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider S. Peter himſelfe: heare what Chriſt ſaith of an houſe built vpon this rocke. <hi>The raine deſcended and the ſlouds came,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>and the windes blew and beat vpon the houſe, and it fell not,</hi> the reaſon followeth, <hi>for it was founded vpon a rocke.</hi> The other quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe being built vpon the vnſtable ſands (and what more vnſtable then a man) <hi>that fell</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and great was the fall of it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 27.</note> both ſuſtained the ſame violence both the ſame flouds, and the ſame tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but ſee where the difference con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154:11"/>not in the ſtuffe, not in the faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not in the maſſe, but onely in the foundation, only in the ſituation. On the other ſide marke S. Peter that great Apoſtle of Chriſt, but alwaies a man, who in this Chapter foure verſes from this whereof we treate,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 23.</note> tooke our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our apart, and was ſo hardy as to rebuke him, becauſe he would needs goe vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hieruſalem: Inſomuch that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in his holy anger was conſtrained to tell him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Get thee behind me Sathan, thou art an offence vnto me, for thou ſavoreſt not the things that bee of God.</hi> If hee was an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or a ſtumbling blocke to Chriſt, how could hee chooſe but bee a cauſe of falling vnto the Church? But ſee him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vpon the point of combate, after ſo many proteſtations of his conſtancie; yea execrations, how hee denies Chriſt with curſes, Chriſt whom before he had ſo hartely confeſſed: and that being far from danger, at the voice of a chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid and of one ſimple dore-keeper; &amp; canſt thou yet imagine him to be hardy enough to withſtand the gates of Hell, which here yeelds himſelfe conquered to a maid of Caiphas? But it is not ſaid that the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt him, but againſt it, againſt the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154:11"/>Church, againſt him only as he is a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt, and a member of that Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6 But here ſome perhaps will ſhake their heads, as If I haue applied my ſelfe too much vnto the letter, vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding only the plaine ſong, inſinuating that there is another tablature, another miſtery in it. Who ought to remember ☜ themſelus of that rule which the fathers giue vs, that there where wee finde one literall and naturall ſenſe ariſing which inſtructeth our faith and manners, and affords no place to any abſurditie, none to any inconvenient or contrary ſenſe, we muſt there ſit downe, without ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching farther through figures, or allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for he which diues lower is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to trouble the cleere water and ſtir the mudde. Nevertheles let vs ſee what it is that they can ſay, what that Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers ſtone is, which they pretend in theſe words, <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi> but withall let vs haue our eies about vs, to diſcerne the falſe coine. <hi>Tu es Petrus,</hi> that is to ſay in the Roman ſpeech (I am ſure neither in Greeke nor Latine) thou art Biſhop of Rome, &amp; vpon thee, as thou art ſuch a one, I will build the Roman Church, and not only vpon thee, not alone vpon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154:12"/>thee <hi>Peter,</hi> for there ſhall bee no more Biſhops of Rome of that name, but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee Gregory, vpon thee Adrian, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander, Iulius &amp;c. vpon every Biſhop of Rome, good or bad, holy or profane, Chriſtian or Atheiſt, be he what he will, I will build the Church, Catholike or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal, viſible in the Roman, infallible in all kinds, &amp; thee ſo much the more as being the head thereof. Here Chriſtian, thou ſeeſt how to ſupply both Rome &amp; the Biſhop of Rome, and ſtand amazed at it, contrary to the intention of him which gaue it, and him which craued it. And indeed, haſt thou no pitty to ſee the word of Chriſt ſo racked, being now made a ſnare to the ſimple, a laughing-ſtocke to the prophane, and blaſphemy to the meredulous. But let vs proceed on a little further; vnder this I ordaine thee Monarch both of things temporal, and things ſpirituall, ſoveraigne king &amp; Biſhop together; of ſpiritual, to controle the old and new Teſtament, to diſpenſe againſt the Goſpell, and againſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, to make new articles of faith, to be aboue all councels, and when thou trayleſt men by thouſands into hell, I would haue no man queſtion thee why doſt thou this? Of temporall to diſpoſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154:12"/>of all the world, to diſtribute it at thy pleaſure, as if it were thine owne heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to raigne over kings, to arraigne &amp; indite them, to depoſe them, to abſolue their ſubiects from their oath of allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to expoſe their eſtates for a pray, their perſons to murther, to beſtow their kingdomes on whom it ſhal pleaſe thee, and laſtly to change their tenures to fealtie, or convert their territories to thine owne demaines. Pitty will here ſtricke thee into honour, though hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly canſt thou beleeue it. But the Ieſuites boaſt conſiſts in this, that of this they are not aſhamed. The bookes of Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, of Eudaemon Iohannes, of Becanus, of Suarez, and of a thouſand others doe ſwell with theſe aſſertions: the Cardinals make them authentique, Bellarmine writing againſt the King of England, &amp; Baronius againſt the Venetians. And the Pope menaceth with fire the edicts of our Parliament, which burne them, &amp; the Sorbone with excommunications, if ſhe reſt not contented with them. Poore deluded Chriſtian, thou never couldeſt well imagine a <hi>protection,</hi> or multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation whereby to reape more profit then an hundred from one, &amp; loe here thou maiſt gaine aboue a thouſand fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:154:13"/>one ſtone: and at this day this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of faith, and ſuch a one, that to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it and overſhadow it, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which the court of Rome leaues vnattempted; ſo that to retaine it, it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not greatly to forgoe halfe her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies; yea to renounce the holy Scriptures, and the articles of all the Creeds. Wouldſt thou fame ſee an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment hereof, thou good Catholike) Goe, confeſſe thy ſelfe vnto a Ieſuite, ſay vnto him, father I am in ſome ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whether I may purchaſe my ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Church of Rome or not? I doubt of Purgatory, of prayer for the dead, becauſe I haue not evidently read them in the Scriptures. After hee hath checkt thee for reading of them, who enforceth thee, ſaith he, to pray for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? and indeed you ſhall never ſee Ieſuits in places of buriall, and in the Abbayes which they poſſeſſe, they little regard the intention of the firſt founders, but convert the profit to other vſes. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith vnto him, Father I haue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to pray vnto Saints, becauſe I ſee no example thereof neither in the olde nor new Teſtament; After hee hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of thee, who in Gods name hath taught thee ſo much: it is not free
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154:13"/>for thee (will he ſay) either to pray, or not to pray vnto them if thou wilt? who wil ſo nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly preſſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trole thee? pray to God &amp; abide in the Church. Likewiſe of the Images, doſt thou not obſerue that in our Churches wee haue few or none, and thoſe we haue are plaine, and little garni hed? But let an <hi>Huguenote</hi> come and ſay thus vnto them, I would willingly accommodate my ſelfe vnto you; many reaſons, and much more inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts doe carry mee on; but I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue this reall preſence; leſſe can I bee perſwaded to adore the hoſt, leaſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I fall into Idolatry; to how many of ſuch kind of men haue they ſaid, ſtand not vpon that, that beleefe will come to you at leaſure. In Spaine it ſelfe they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue not men ſo narrowly, for ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the hoſt ſtanding; Turne a new leaſe, and albeit that thou beeſt a good Catholike, yet if thou ſaiſt vnto them, Father, I doubt ſomewhat of the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of the Pope, and of that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, whether it hath ſo large an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent as ſome make it to haue; theſe tearmes of his being Gods vicegerent, of his omnipotency, doe wound my conſcience; they are ſtraight in an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roare, an inexpiable blaſphemie, and an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154:14"/>Anatheme. If thou thinkeſt but to dull the edge of this blade, or bend this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſword; if thou receaveſt not the thruſt of it with thy naked breaſt, thou art a dead man; hadſt thou ſaith enough to remooue mountaines from one place to another, hadſt thou as much charitie as to ſuffer thy ſelfe to be burnt for thy brethren, yet the Ocean were it turned all into holy water, could not expiate thee, there is no peace for thee in this life, nor remiſſion in the world to come.</p>
            <p n="7">7 This article notwithſtanding can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be drawne from this place: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ☞ to it, all that which followeth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Scripture is contrary; for betweene theſe words <hi>Tu es Petrus, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Paulus Quintus is Monarch of things both temporall and spiritua.</hi> what depthes haue they to fill, how many Theſes to prooue, and ſyllogiſmes to compoſe? as firſt, that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was at Rome, that there hee conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted his Apoſtolicall Sea, that as being Biſhop of Rome Chriſt conferred vpon him that Monarchy: that hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue him authorititie to bequeath it to his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and that this Pope which now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſucceeds him in his Chaire, his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and his doctrine; of which they ſhall never bee able ſufficiently to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154:14"/>the leaſt: And as for the Scripture it is altogether contrary vnto it. For co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſpirituall power, Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that which we here handle, cuts of the queſtion which aroſe from the ambition <hi>of the ſonnes of Zebedie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.26.</note> 
               <hi>whoſoever will be great amongſt you, let him be your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, &amp;c.</hi> And the Diſciples which often mooued this doubt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.34.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhould bee the greateſt amongſt them,</hi> one while vpon the way, another while vpon the point of his paſſion, preſuppoſed not that it was Peter, becauſe they had not yet appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the myſtery which ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to find in this paſſage, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſh ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Saviour to propoſe vnto them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.33. <hi>Luk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> ſometimes the conditions of a little child for their example, ſometim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to menace the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ruine, if here on earth they ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtained aſpiring cogitations, ſometimes to ſuggeſt vnto them that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e which they ſhould hold on high in his kingdome, and all but to diver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them from theſe imaginary Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies. S. Paule likewiſe ſpeakes freely. That he built vpon no other mans<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that hee was nothing inferiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto Peter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and that hee withſtood him to the face: but Peter himſelfe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the reſurrection of our Lord, then
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154:15"/>when it behoved his Vicar moſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> al, to manifeſt himſelt vnto the world, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not <hi>pleno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure</hi> for the Apoſtleſhip of <hi>Iudas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 1.15.</note> was not preſident in the Councell of the Apoſtles h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld at Hieruſalem, but on the contrary ſide ſubmitted himſelfe to be ſent, tooke commiſſion from his brethren the Apoſtles, and rendred him ſelfe as companion of the elders to feed the flocke.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>The elders ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, I exhort, who am alſo an elder &amp;c: feed the flocke of God which is among you ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the overſight thereof, &amp;c: not as being L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds over Gods heritage,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>but being examples to the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, and when the chiefe ſhephend ſhall appeare, yee ſhall recei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a crowd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th not away.</hi> Where we note that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred himſelfe often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the leſſon of that ſoveraigne Paſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our Lord Ieſus, who had ſaid vnto them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.25.</note> 
               <hi>the princes of the Gentiles exerc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minion in or them,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>but it ſhall not be ſo with you,</hi> for he vſed the ſame verbe. And as for the temporall power he told them &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto them throughout, <hi>that his kingdome was not of the world, and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is not greater then his maſter,</hi> not therefore the kingdome of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Vicar, be he the Biſhop of Rome, or <hi>S. Peter</hi> himſelfe. And <hi>S. Paul</hi> excludes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154:15"/>no perſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>let every ſoule</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto the higher powers,</hi> that is to ſay, (ſay the fathers) whoſoever thou beeſt, Prophet, Evangeliſt, or Apoſtle. And <hi>S. Peter</hi> himſelfe at the greateſt ſtrength of his pretended empire, bids vs, <hi>feare God, and honour the king.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17.</note> And what king-<hi>Nero</hi> a perſecutor of the Church, a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the common wealth, and plague of mankinde; now if he had a materia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l ſword, till when reſerved he it, till when kept he his thunderbolts?</p>
            <p n="8">8 Alſo we doe ſee, from that naturall and ancient interpretation which wee propoſed aboue, what conſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns haue redounded vnto the Chriſtian Church, and to all his members: on the other ſide from this later, ſince the time that Gregory the 7. called Hildebrand, vented it, there proceeded nothing but extreame deſolations, the ſubiect revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the prince, the brother a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the brother, the ſonne againſt the father, the cleargie againſt the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the prieſthood againſt the empire, ſupplantations, treaſons, butcheries, through the fields and the citties, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended zeales, maskes of religion, blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy tragedies. And ſince that in our daies men haue preſſed it vnto the laſt iſſue, they haue extracted its quinteſſence
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154:16"/>through the limbicke of the Ieſuites &amp; we know to whome we are bound for it, who haue ſeene this kingdome mantled with aſhes and blood; and in 20. yeares two Kings aſſaſinated (God preſerue the third) a thing not ſeen in ten ages before.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Here one perhaps will demaund how ſo prodigious a doctrine as this is, hath found a place, and that vpon one word only of Chriſts? marke the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. A great workman to ſhew a tricke of his arte, builds a whole peace, ſetting out and teſting vpon one ſtone onely (this they call <hi>Promp llo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> he interlaceth and indent, the inciſions and ioyntures within, preſents it vnto thee, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth thee with falſe ioynts without, to ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke thee to an aſtoniſhment, and to conceale his ſtructure. Sathan here doth iuſt the ſame, endeavouring as an ape to imitate the ſon of God. To couzen the world, he enterpriſeth to build his ſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue (the principle worke of his art) vpon this one poore word, <hi>Peter,</hi> that he may raiſe it aboue, and faſten his ſtones one within another to wit the Princes with the Biſhops, the people againſt the Princes, he beautifies his building with the ambition of prelates, with the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of princes, with the ignorance of the common people, and puts all theſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154:16"/>pieces into his worke. And thoſe falſe ioynts conſiſt in monopolies, in ſleights of flattery, in the profanations of the name of Chriſt, in deriſion of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, euen of the Sonne of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d vpon the Croſſe for our ſakes: theſe they diſguiſe, theſe they couer from our view with paſſages of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, with them they bring their worke vnto the roofe, euen to the weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke. And ſuch kind of words are theſe, <hi>Tu es Petrus,</hi> ſuch are <hi>Paſce oues meas,</hi> ſuch, <hi>occide, &amp; mandica,</hi> with many others. Aske any good Doctor of the Sorbon what the meaning of theſe words is, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſce oues meas,</hi> feede my ſheepe; hee vvill reade his Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Gloſſe, and then he will tell thee, <hi>feede them, verbo &amp; exemplo,</hi> both with word and example. The good man knowes not that in the Romane lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage it is as much to ſay now adayes <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n currentem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.13.</note> as the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et goes, manage the Kings and Princes with the ſwitch. Aske another what ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies that voice ſpoken of <hi>Peter,</hi> in the Acts, <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h &amp; ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> kill and eate, he wil remember himſelfe of that veſſel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from heauen, which was pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented vnto him in a viſion, in the which were all ſorts of liuing creatures, both o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:154:17"/>the land and water; and of the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> being taught by the Spirit of God, gaue vnto it: that the time of calling the Gentiles vvas come, that he ſhould <hi>not ſay any were that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ve ſ.</hi> 28.</note> or make a di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ference betweene lew and Greeke, Greek &amp; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>banan; he knowes not the ſecret which Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> hath fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d heere, Kill and deuour thoſe creatures, the Kings and Princes, which performe not that vvhich thou haſt enjoyned them, for thus doe they prophane theſe words, and in the mean time behold the bookes which at this day are moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and in greateſt authoritie, ſee how vnder the skinne of the Lambe of God, are hid Wolues and Lions, vvhich counterfeit a ſweete voice, in horrible howlings, vnder the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſword of Chriſts word, they forge this temporall ſword, and maintaine it with their denoted &amp; execrable kniues.</p>
            <p n="10">10 So th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n we ſee how through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Satan we haue been carried vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſleepe, from our ſauing rock tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported vpon the diſmall rocke of Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s, and that vnder the colour of a wreſted interpretation, miſchieuouſly inuented, by ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lth inſinuated, lightly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>d, which hath paſſed amongſt the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154:17"/>ſimple, as being the cry of the citie in a popular errour, (for what is it but a prime imagination giuen to our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to conceiue the bells to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, and Heluetian tabours to play whatſoeuer they imagine: and it is a like illuſion to vs, to make vs ſee in ſuch places of the Scripture as theſe, all that which ſhall make for them: &amp; neuertheleſſe we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend about it, as vpon an article of faith, and combate more thereon, then vpon all the Creed beſides. Wherefore let vs hold vs to the ancient expoſition, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more ſimple, I am ſure, more ſafe, and let vs not feare at al, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> can ſuſtaine any damage thereby. Our Sauiour Chriſt demanded of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e anſwered him, Thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God. Thou art Chriſt the annoynted of the Lord, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed from the beginning of ages vnto our fathers, declared from time to time by his prophets, expected in our time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the ſalvation of the world, not a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Monarch, ſuch a one as theſe Phariſes prefigure, but the eternall Son of God, only able to ſatiſfie his iuſtice, to moue his compaſſion, to ſecure vs from his wrath, to purchaſe vs &amp; to merit vs his grace; and what anſwere doth out Lord make him, I ſay vnto thee that thou
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154:18"/>art Peter, that I haue choſen thee to make thee a liuing ſtone in the building which I haue prepared me in my church. But where ſhall I build in my father hath revealed vnto thee one ſecret, and I will teach thee another, grace vpon grace. Verily vpon that Chriſt, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſonne of God which thou haſt confeſſed, that Ieſus which thou ſeeſt, a quickning ſtone an immoueable and eternall rocke, to ſtand againſt the th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>derbolts of the an e the raging<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea, the ſhakings of the earth, the powers of hell, be it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eated where it will, it ſhall be aboue it, fixed, &amp; founded in the midſt of heaven: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r ſixteen hundred yeares after, the hiſtory of the church addeth credit vnto this: feare not, Chriſtian, whatſoever thou ſeeſt, be not diſmaid. The Church ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſcantled to 8 perſons in the arke, peopled afterwardes the whole earth; ſometimes incloſed in the ſepulchre, as was her head, through her head was ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred vp and fully reſtored. Chriſt hath ſaid it, that eternall word; Chriſt hath done it, that ſonne by whome the father made the world;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8.</note> Chriſt will doe it <hi>yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday and to day</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and the ſame for ever;</hi> to whom with the father and the holy ghoſt, be honor and glory world without end; <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
